<?xml version="1.0"?>

<rules xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation='whq-rules-schema.xsd'>
  <rule id="rpb-ambush" name="AMBUSH"><p>Some Monsters are able to Ambush the Warriors, springing from the darkness and attacking them before they have the chance to react.</p>
<p>Each type of Monster with the Ambush ability has an Ambush Rating (n) that shows the score they need on 106 to successfully spring their Ambush. Daemonettes of Slaanesh, for instance, have Ambush 5+, and therefore need a score of 5 or 6 on 1D6 to successfully Ambush the Warriors. An Ambush Rating of 'A' indicates that the Monster automatically succeeds in making its Ambush and doesn't need to roll.</p>
<p>Monsters that successfully carry out an Ambush may ignore the rule about waiting until the next Monsters' Phase before they attack. If the Monsters appear in the Power Phase, for instance, they are placed and make one set of attacks in that phase and attack in the Monsters' Phase. Once such Monsters have sprung their ambush they fight only in the Monsters' Phase from then on, as normal.</p>
<p>Note that as any sort of attach may be an Ambush, special abilities that are also Ambushes are indicated with the suffix 'Ambush' in the Monster Tables.</p>
<p>A Hydra, for instance, has the Breathe Fire 4 (Ambush A) Special Ability, indicating that it makes an automatically successful Ambush with its 4D6 damage Breathe Fire attack when it is first placed on the board.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-ambush-magic" name="AMBUSH, MAGIC n+"><p>Some Monsters are blindingly fast at making their attacks, and can make a Magic Ambush. A Magic Ambush works in exactly the same way as an Ambush, above, except that if the Monsters succeed it is impossible even for the Wizard (or any other spellcaster) to unleash a spell before their attacks start!</p>
<p>In addition, if the Monster making the Magic Ambush is a spellcaster, in the first turn it may cast an extra set of spells as soon as it is placed.</p>
<p>Those special abilities that are also Magical Ambushes are given the suffix 'Ambush, Magic'.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-armed-with" name="ARMED WITH weapon (STR n)"><p>Some Monsters are Armed With special weapons. Rules for such items are usually contained under that Monster's description or in the Equipment Tables and you should refer to those sections for more details. In most cases such weapons simply replace the Monster's Strength, indicated by a Strength modifier (n) contained in brackets after this entry.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-armed-with-choice" name="ARMED WITH [a-b] weapon1 OR [c-d] weapon2."><p>Some Monsters may be Armed With a choice of weapons. This entry indicates that on a 106 roll in the range a-b these Monsters are armed with weaponl and in the range c-d they are armed with weapon2.</p>
<p>For example, entry 43 on the Level 2 Monster Table for Goblins reads: Armed with [1-3] Bows (Str 1) or [4-6] Spears (Fight In Ranks). This indicates that on a 1D6 roll of 1, 2 or 3 all of the Goblins in the group are armed with Bows of Strength 1, while on a 4, 5 or 6 they are armed with Spears.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-assassinate" name="ASSASSINATE n+"><p>Some Monsters may make a special Assassinate attack. This is treated like a normal hand-to-hand combat attack except when resolving damage the blow ignores the target's armour. In addition, if the to hit roll was a natural roll of n+, where n+ is the number following the Assassinate entry (if there is one), the blow also ignores the target's Toughness. For example, 'Assassinate 6+' means ignore Toughness and armour on a to hit roll of 6.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-break" name="BREAK"><p>Some Monsters are innately cowardly, and if the fight is going badly will turn tail and run. These Monsters have a Break Point.</p>
<p>At the end of each turn during which one or more Monsters with a Break Point were killed, roll 1D6 for each different type that took casualties. If the score is greater than or equal to the remaining number of that type of Monster, they break and run, vanishing into the shadows - remove them from the board.</p>
<p>The Warriors do not get the Gold Value for any Monsters that run away, though they do get a Treasure card at the end of the combat, as usual.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-breathe-fire" name="BREATHE FIRE n"><p>Some Monsters can Breathe Fire. Each type of Monster with the Breathe Fire ability has a Fire Breath Strength Rating (n) that shows the attack's damage. At the start of each turn roll 1D6. The number rolled indicates how many of the Warriors are engulfed in flame. If the score is higher than the number of Warriors present all of them have been hit. If not all of them are hit use the Warrior counters to determine who escapes.</p>
<p>Each Warrior hit by the fire suffers nD6 Wounds, with no modifier for armour (where n is the Monster's Fire Breath Strength Rating). A Hydra, for instance, does 4D6 damage.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-chill" name="CHILL n"><p>Some Monsters make a special Chill attack rather than a normal hand-to-hand combat attack. Such Monsters make a to hit roll as normal, but when determining damage they simply cause nD6 Wounds with no modifiers for Toughness or armour (where n is the number after the Chill entry). For example, 'Chill 4' means the Monster causes 4D6 Wounds.</p>
<p>In addition, if the target is reduced to 0 Wounds by a Chill attack he is immediately killed and may only be healed by spells and magic items that actually raise their target from the dead rather than heal him, such as the Resurrection Spell.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-daemonic" name="DAEMONIC n"><p>Some Monsters are of Daemonic origin and as such are very difficult to hit. When making an attack with a non-magical weapon against such a creature, your Warrior's to hit rolls are reduced by n, where n is the number after the Daemonic entry. Attacks with magical weapons are made as normal.</p>
<p>A Monster with Daemonic -2, for instance, reduces its opponent's to hit roll by 2.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-dodge" name="DODGE n+"><p>Some Monsters are able to Dodge in the same way as the Elf Warrior. Each type of Monster with the Dodge ability has a Dodge Rating (n+) that shows the score they need on 1D6 to successfully dodge an incoming blow.</p>
<p>A Monster with Dodge 5+, for instance, avoids a Warrior's attack on a 1D6 roll of 5 or 6.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-ethereal" name="ETHEREAL n"><p>Some Monsters, such as Wights, are insubstantial, Ethereal beings. Such Monsters can never be pinned, and may move freely through other Monsters and obstacles as if they weren't there. In addition, when making an attack with a non-magical weapon against such a creature, your Warrior's to hit rolls are reduced by n. where n is the number after the Ethereal entry. Attacks with magic weapons are made as normal.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-fatal-damage" name="FATAL DAMAGE"><p>Some Monsters' attacks and items, such as Tomb Rot and Venom Armour, inflict a special sort of damage called Fatal Damage. This works in exactly the same way as normal damage, but is calculated at the very end of the turn and thus after all of that turn's healing has been done. This means that a Warrior that takes enough Fatal Damage to take him to 0 Wounds or below has no last chance to heal it and is thus automatically killed.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-fear" name="FEAR n"><p>Some Monsters cause Fear because they are particularly frightening for one reason or another. Zombies, for instance, are the re-animated corpses of oncehuman Warriors and are terribly fearsome to face in combat. Minotaurs, on the other hand, cause Fear because of their sheer size and ferocity.</p>
<p>Each Monster that causes Fear also has a Fear Value, indicated by the n after the Fear entry. When an event occurs that generates Monsters that cause Fear, roll 1D6+ (the Warrior's Battle-level) for each Warrior that wants to attack a fear-causing Monster. This is the Warrior's Fear roll.</p>
<p>If the total is greater than the Monsters' Fear Value, that Warrior is not afraid of them during this combat and may fight them as normal.</p>
<p>If the total is less than or equal to the Monsters' Fear Value, that Warrior is afraid of them during this combat, and fights them at -1 on his to hit rolls. If a Wizard fails his Fear roll any spells he attempts to cast against that Monster have their Casting Numbers increased by +1.</p>
<p>Each time the Warriors meet a particular type of Monster that causes Fear they must make a Fear roll, as the effect of the roll, whether good or bad, applies only to that type of Monster during this one combat.</p>
<p>If there are two types of Monster in the room that cause Fear, make a Fear roll for each Warrior against the particular Monster he is fighting.</p>
<p>Note that in the higher level Monster Tables some Monsters, such as Minotaurs, no longer cause Fear. This is because the Warriors are no longer so frightened of them, given that nearly every other Monster on that level of the dungeon is much bigger, tougher and nastier.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-fight-in-ranks" name="FIGHT IN RANKS"><p>Some Monsters, such as Goblins with spears, are armed with weapons that allow them to Fight in Ranks: to engage an opponent in hand-to-hand combat from 2 squares away, as long as the square between is either empty or contains friendly models. The diagram on the right explains this more clearly.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-fly" name="FLY"><p>Some Monsters are able to Fly, and thus can move around the board with a greater degree of freedom. Monsters that can Fly may move to any empty square on the board within their Movement range, ignoring all obstacles in their way.</p>
<p>Monsters that fly may not be pinned in combat and may change their target each turn. Draw a Warrior counter at the start of each Monsters' Phase for each flying Monster to determine which Warrior it attacks. (If there isn't an empty square next to the intended victim, draw again.)</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-frenzy" name="FRENZY n+"><p>Some Monsters are subject to Frenzy. Each turn, before combat, such a Monster may enter a state of utter rage. Roll 1D6. If the score is equal to or over n, where n is the Monster's Frenzy Rating (given after the Frenzy entry), the Monster gets 2 x its normal number of Attacks for the rest of the combat.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-gang-up" name="GANG UP"><p>Some Monsters can Gang Up on the Warriors, hoping to use strength in numbers to defeat their opponents.</p>
<p>Rather than distributing such Monsters evenly amongst the Warriors when you place them on the board, draw a Warrior counter and place as many of the Monsters as you can around that Warrior. If there are any Monsters left, draw another Warrior counter and place as many Monsters as you can around him. Repeat this process until all the Monsters are placed on the board.</p>
<p>Each group of Monsters surrounding a single Warrior makes one single combined attack for each Attack in their profile: each group of Nurglings therefore, for example, makes 2 combined Attacks. Count up the number of Monsters attacking each Warrior. For every Monster above one in contact with the Warrior, add +1 to the to hit roll and increase the Strength of the Monsters' attack by +1.</p>
<p>For instance, if there are 4 Snotlings ganging up on the Barbarian they get a single Strength 4 attack with +3 on the to hit roll. Once they have started attacking, Monsters that Gang Up do not switch attacks until either they are all dead, or the Warrior is killed.</p>
<p>When defending themselves, each Monster in the gang fights individually, with the Weapon Skill Indicated on its profile.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-greater-daemon" name="GREATER DAEMON n"><p>Some Monsters are termed Greater Daemons because they are the most powerful creatures of daemonic origin. When making an attack with a nonmagical weapon against such a creature, your Warrior's to hit rolls are reduced by -2. Attacks made with magical weapons are at -1.</p>
<p>Each Greater Daemon also has a Greater Daemon Terror Value, indicated by the n after the Greater Daemon entry. At the start of a combat that there is a Greater Daemon on the board roll 1D6+(your Warrior's Battle-level) for each Warrior. This is the Warrior's Greater Daemon Terror roll. If the total is greater than the Greater Daemon's Terror Value, that Warrior is not afraid of it during this combat and may fight it as normal.</p>
<p>If the total is less than or equal to the Greater Daemon's Terror Value, and wasn't a natural roll of 1, that Warrior is terrified of it during this combat, and fights it at a further -2 on his to hit rolls. If a Wizard fails his Greater Daemon Terror roll any spells he attempts to cast against it have their Casting Number increased by +2.</p>
<p>If your Warrior's roll was a natural 1 he is so terrified that he may do nothing at all for 1 turn and may be hit automatically.</p>
<p>If it is a magic user, when rolling for spells a Greater Daemon gets +1 on its Magic Table dice roll. Note that Greater Daemons normally use the Chaos Magic table: see the Chaos Sorcerer entry in the Chaos section for full details.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-guards" name="GUARDS (monster)"><p>On certain occasions Monsters are listed as Guards because, as the term suggests, they are. guarding one or more of the other Monsters that they are placed with. They must be placed so that they surround the Monster they are guarding (given in brackets after the Guards entry).</p>
<p>Once placed, Guards stand their ground and will not move towards the Warriors unless the Monster they are protecting is slain. They may fire any missile weapons they have as normal.</p>
<p>If the Monster the Guards are protecting is slain they become so enraged that they get +1 Attack for the rest of the combat.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-hate" name="HATE race"><p>Some Monsters Hate certain types of Warrior (shown by the race, above). Dark Elves, for instance, Hate Elves. If a Monster Hates a particular Warrior, it will attack him with unbridled ferocity. The Monster gains +1 Attacks when fighting that Warrior, as he slashes and hacks in a mad bloodlust. His attacks are so wild, however, that they are made at 1 to hit.</p>
<p>In a similar manner, if a Warrior Hates a particular type of Monster he gets +1 Attacks made at -1 to hit against them.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-hypnotise" name="HYPNOTISE n+"><p>Some Monsters are able to Hypnotise their foes, holding them immobile while they attack them. Each Monster with this ability has a Hypnotism Rating (n+) that is the number required on a roll of 1D6 for the attack to work. A hypnotised Warrior may fight as normal, but is prevented from trying to escape from pinning (and that includes the Elf!).</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-ignore-blows" name="IGNORE BLOWS n+"><p>Some Monsters are so immense and powerful that they can Ignore Blows which would kill lesser Monsters. Each time a Warrior hits such a Monster in hand-to-hand combat or with a missile weapon roll 1D6. If the score is equal to or higher than its Ignore Blow Rating (n+) the hit is shrugged off and causes no damage at all.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-ignore-pain" name="IGNORE PAIN n"><p>Some Monsters are so large that they can Ignore Pain caused by all but the most powerful blows. Each time a Warrior hits Such a Monster in hand-tohand combat or with a missile weapon subtract its Ignore Pain Rating (n) from the number of Wounds caused (in addition to subtracting its Toughness and any armour it is wearing, if applicable).</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-large-monster" name="LARGE MONSTER"><p>Some Monsters are so big that they are known by the special term Large Monster. Obvious examples are Dragons and Giants. When placing a Large Monster on the board draw a Warrior counter. That player places the model anywhere on the board, facing any direction and moving other Monsters or Warriors to make room as required. Then draw a second Warrior counter to determine who the Monster attacks.</p>
<p>Any offensive spells cast against a Large Monster require a number of extra points of Power, equal to the level of the Monster table that generated the Monster, to cast.</p>
<p>If a Large Monster manages to kill a Warrior and still has some unused Attacks left over it may choose any other available target and carry on.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-magic" name="Type MAGIC n"><p>Some Monsters have the ability to use Magic, although the spells available to them depend on their race. The descriptions of these Monsters in the Bestiary contains the spells they use.</p>
<p>Monsters with this ability also have a Magic Rating (n) that indicates how many spells they can cast per turn. A Chaos Dwarf Sorcerer with Chaos Dwarf Magic 3, for instance, can cast 3 spells each turn from those spells available to him. Monsters with spell-casting ability do not use Power in the same way as the Wizard.</p>
<p>Magic-using Monsters are placed on the board as if they were using missile weapons and, unless otherwise stated, are always placed first.</p>
<p>In addition, all magic-using Monsters protect themselves with minor spells that make them harder to hit from a distance. All missile weapon attacks made against magic-using Monsters are at -1 on the to hit roll.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-magic-dispel" name="MAGIC DISPEL n+"><p>Some Monsters have the ability to Dispel Magic in the surrounding area. This differs from the Magic Resistance special ability in that the Monster can actively interfere with and nullify any spell, not just those cast directly against it.</p>
<p>A Monster with this attribute has a Magical Dispel Rating (n+), that is the number required on a roll of 1D6 for the ability to work. The dice roll is made as soon as the targeted spell is cast. If the roll is equal to or greater than the Monster's Magic Dispel Rating, the spell has no effect at all and the Power used to cast it is wasted.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-magic-drain" name="MAGIC DRAIN n+"><p>Some Monsters can soak up or Drain Magic from the air around them, rendering any spellcasting impossible while they remain alive. A Monster with this attribute has a Magic Drain Rating (n+), which is the number required on a roll of 1D6 for the ability to work. The effect covers the whole board. Roll once per turn during the Power Phase, immediately after determining the Wizard's Power. If successful, the Wizard loses all his Power for that turn.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-magic-resistance" name="MAGIC RESISTANCE n+"><p>Some Monsters are naturally able to shrug off the effects of a spell cast against them. Such Monsters are said to have Magic Resistance.</p>
<p>A Monster with this ability has a Magic Resistance Rating (n+) that is the number required on a roll of 1D6 for the protection to work. This roll is the Monster's Resistance roll. A separate Resistance roll should be made for each spell cast against the Monster. If the roll succeeds the effects of the spell may be ignored by that particular Monster. If more than one Monster with this ability can be affected by the spell, roll for each Monster individually. Note that Magic Resistance only protects the Monster from spells, not from blows by magical weapons and the like.</p>
<p>Note that some Monsters' Magic Resistance is not an innate ability, but is due to an item or charm they wear or carry. Where this is the case, the Magic Resistance entry is suffixed with the item that provides the protection.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-magic-armour" name="MAGIC ARMOUR"><p>Some Monsters wear Magic Armour that confers special abilities on them, just like the magic armour that the Warriors possess. In the Monsters' case though these hell-forged items are evil and corrupted and will destroy any Warrior who tries to wear or take them.</p>
<p>If the Monster's entry indicates that it has magic armour roll 1D6 on the following table to determine what it is. A group of the same type of Monsters has the same magic armour, so you should roll for the group as a whole.</p>
<table>
<tr><td>1</td><td>Chaos Armour. Every time the wearer is struck roll 1D6. On a score of 4, 5 or 6 the blow causes no damage. In addition, the wearer has Magic Resistance 5+.</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>Armour of Cursed Iron. This armour adds the value of the attacker's Strength to the wearer's Toughness, effectively cancelling it out. If the attacker has a Strength of 5, for instance, the armour gives the wearer +5 Toughness.</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>Armour of Doom. The magical field surrounding this armour and its wearer slows down any Warrior attacking the wearer. Any Warrior attacking a Monster who wears Armour of Doom suffers -1 to hit and -1 attacks.</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>Arcane Armour of Destruction. The powerful dark energies flowing within this armour strike back at its attackers. Each time a Warrior attacks a Monster wearing this armour and causes damage roll 1D6. On a score of a 1 the blow is thrown back at the Warrior as a blast of magical energy. He immediately suffers the Wounds he has just inflicted instead, modified for Toughness and armour.</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td>Venom Armour. At the end of every turn in which a Warrior remains adjacent to the wearer of this armour he stands a chance of being poisoned by the venom that constantly oozes from it. Roll 1D6. If the score is a 1. 2 or 3 your Warrior takes 1D6 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour. This attack is Fatal Damage.</td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td>Armour of Carnage. This armour gives the wearer +2 Toughness. In addition, it has a bloodthirsty will of its own, and forces its wearer into battle, even if he is actually dead. While the wearer lives the armour gives him +1 Attacks. Upon the wearer's death, roll 1D6 at the start of every subsequent turn. On a score of 1 or 2 the armour crashes to the floor, empty and dead. On a score of 3, 4, 5 or 6 the armour keeps fighting by itself, animated by the powerful magic within it. The armour has the same profile as the wearer, but only has one Attack. Any further Wounds inflicted on the armour have no effect at all.</td></tr>
</table>
<p>Note that Warriors' weapons that bypass armour only ignore the Toughness bonus the armour confers, not any other magic qualities it may possess. For example, a Bull Centaur Champion has Armour 2, and 'Magic Armour'. This means that as well as having armour that gives it +2 Toughness, the Bull Centaur's armour is magic too. If a Warrior using a sword that ignores armour hits the Bull Centaur, he ignores the Toughness bonus, but not any special magic abilities of the Monster's armour.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-magic-item" name="MAGIC ITEM"><p>Some Monsters carry Magic Items, just like the magic items that the Warriors possess. In the Monsters' case though these items are cursed and are useless to the Warriors.</p>
<p>If the Monster's entry indicates that it carries a magic item roll 1D6 on the following table to determine what it is. A group of the same type of Monsters have the same magic items, so you should roll for the group as a whole. If a Monster's entry indicates it gets multiple items, each of the Monsters in the group gets the same set of items, re-rolling duplicate items.</p>
<p>If an item has an offensive capability it makes an extra attack during the Monsters' Phase. The effects of all these items cannot be dispelled.</p>
<table>
<tr><td>1</td><td>Ring of Resistance. This ring gives the wearer Magic Resistance 6+. If the wearer already has the Magic Resistance special ability it improves his Magic Resistance Rating by +1.</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>Cloak of Shadows. All Warriors attempting to hit the wearer of this cloak are at -1 to their to hit rolls.</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>Warpstone Talisman. Whenever a Warrior rolls a natural 1 on his to hit roll against the wearer of this talisman the blow rebounds at full effect and he hits himself instead.</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>Doomfire Ring. The wearer may use this ring to fire a bolt of power at one of the Warriors each turn. Draw a Warrior counter to determine who is targeted. Then make a roll to hit with a Ballistic Skill of 4+. If the attack hits, the target suffers 2D6+(2 x the Dungeon level) Wounds, with no modifier for armour.</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td>Mask of Radon. This mask gives the wearer Fear (Dungeon Level +3). If the wearer already causes Fear it gives him Terror (his Fear Value).</td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td>Collar of Vengeance. Any Warrior adjacent to the wearer at the end of the turn suffers 1D6 Wounds with no modifiers for Toughness or armour. This is Fatal Damage.</td></tr>
</table>
</rule>
  <rule id="rpb-magic-weapon" name="MAGIC WEAPON"><p>Some Monsters bear a Magic Weapon, just like the magic weapons that the Warriors possess. In the Monsters' case though these items are cursed and will destroy any Warrior who tries to use them.</p>
<p>If the Monster's entry indicates that it carries a magic weapon roll 1D6 on the following table to determine what it is. A group of the same type of Monsters have the same magic weapons, so you should roll for the group as a whole.</p>
<table>
<tr><td>1</td><td><b>Cutting Edge Sword.</b> This sword causes (+1 Wounds x the bearer's level). A Monster rolled on the Level 3 Monster Table, for instance, inflicts an extra +3 Wounds.</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td><b>Sword of Distortion.</b> This sword causes the wielder's outline to shimmer, making him harder to hit. Any Warrior attempting to attack a Monster hearing this sword deducts -1 from his to hit rolls. In addition, the warping nature of this sword reduces the effect of any blows that actually strike the Monster, effectively giving it +1 Toughness.</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td><b>Sword of Pain.</b> This sword ignores any non-magical armour and up to 3 points of magical armour when determining damage.</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td><b>Cursed Blackblade.</b> This sword warps time around the immediate vicinity of its wielder. Once per turn you may re-roll the bearer's first attack that misses. In addition, this sword causes an extra +lD6 Wounds.</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td><b>Sword of Insanity.</b> This sword gives the bearer a Fear Value equal to twice the Battle-level of the Warrior he is fighting. If the Monster wielding this sword already causes Fear it gives him a Terror Value equal to its original Fear Value.</td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td><b>Blade of the Damned.</b> This blade causes double damage every time it strikes. (Roll the normal amount of damage, multiply the result by 2 and then add the wielder's Str.)</td></tr>
</table>
</rule>
  <rule id="rpb-never-pinned" name="NEVER PINNED"><p>Some Monsters are Never Pinned and may move around in combat as they please.</p>
<p>If the Monsters in question are missile troops, each turn they will try to move to a location which allows them to take a shot. Draw a Warrior counter for each Monster to determine which Warrior it targets.</p>
<p>If the Monsters are armed with hand-to-hand weapons, draw a Warrior counter each turn for each of them to determine which Warriors they move towards and attack.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-paralysis" name="PARALYSIS"><p>In addition to causing normal damage when they attack, some Monsters cause Paralysis. At the end of each turn in which your Warrior is wounded by such a Monster deduct 1 from his Movement. If a Warrior is reduced to 0 Movement he is killed and is removed from play. At the start each turn after that in which your Warrior was first struck roll 1D6 and add his Strength. If the score is 8 or greater the paralysis wears off and his Movement returns to its starting value. If the Warrior survives the combat, once there are no Monsters left on the board the paralysis wears off automatically and his Movement returns to normal. Paralysis can also be cured by a healing spell or healing potion, but not by bandages or provisions, or the like.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-parry" name="PARRY n"><p>Some Monsters can Parry a Warrior's hand-to-hand attacks so that they don't cause any damage. Each time such a Monster is attacked roll 1D6. If the score is n or above, where n is the Parry Value after the Parry entry, the Monster turns the blow and it causes no damage.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-petrify" name="PETRIFY"><p>Some Monsters can Petrify their foes in combat, turning them to stone with a single gaze. Any Warrior that attacks such a Monster is at -2 to his to hit rolls as he is so busy trying to avoid its gaze.</p>
<p>In addition, if a Warrior attacking a Monster with a Petrify attack scores a natural 1 on his to hit roll he has been caught by the creature's gaze and starts to turn to stone. He immediately suffers 3D6 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour, and for the rest of the adventure he is at -1 Movement. If his Movement is subsequently reduced to 0 by any means while in the dungeon he is immediately turned to stone, beyond all reach of healing magic.</p>
<p>All Monsters with a Petrify attack also have natural Magic Resistance 4+ and, if their Resistance Roll is a natural 6, may immediately turn their Petrify attack on the spellcaster that attacked them and inflict the effects given above.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-plague" name="PLAGUE"><p>Some Monsters carry a horrible, disfiguring disease known simply as the Plague and may infect their opponents with it in combat. If your Warrior is reduced to 0 Wounds by such a Monster his Toughness is permanently reduced by -1 when he is healed to 1 or more Wounds. If a Warrior is reduced to 0 Toughness he is killed and removed from play.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-poison" name="POISON"><p>Some Monsters have Poison attacks. If a Warrior is reduced to 0 Wounds by a Poison attack his Strength is permanently reduced by -1 when he is healed to 1 or more Wounds. If a Warrior is reduced to 0 Strength he is killed and removed from play.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-protection-ring" name="PROTECTION RING (+n T)"><p>Some Monsters wear magical rings that give them an extra +n Toughness, where n is the number in the brackets following the Protection Ring entry.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-regenerate" name="REGENERATE n"><p>Some Monsters can Regenerate Wounds while they remain alive, making them much harder to kill. Each Monster with this ability has a Regeneration Rating (n+) that is the number of D6 Wounds that the Monster regains at the end of each turn.</p>
<p>A Monster with Regenerate 2, for instance, regains 2D6 Wounds at the end of each turn.</p>
<p>A Monster cannot regenerate if it is reduced to 0 Wounds or fewer and can never have more Wounds than it started with (except Vampires).</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-sting" name="STING (damage)"><p>Some Monsters may Sting their opponents, but only if all of their normal attacks hit in a single turn. The sting does the damage indicated in the brackets after the Sting entry. Sting attacks are also subject to the rules for Poison attacks, above.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-tattoos" name="TATTOOS n+"><p>Some Monsters are painted with complicated protective Tattoos that act like armour. Whether this is due to some arcane power inherent in the tattoos, or simply the strength of belief on the wearer's part, they do seem to work.</p>
<p>Each time a Monster wearing tattoos is hit roll 1D6. If the score is n or more, where n is the number after the Tattoos entry, the blow has no effect.</p>
<p>A Monster with Tattoos 5+, for instance, ignores incoming blows on a 1D6 roll of 5 or 6.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-terror" name="TERROR n"><p>Some Monsters cause Terror. This is similar to Fear, only much, much worse.</p>
<p>Each Monster that causes Terror has a Terror Value, indicated by the n after the Terror entry. When an event occurs that generates Monsters that cause Terror, roll 1D6+(your Warrior's Battle-level) for each Warrior as soon as the Monsters are placed on the board. This is the Warrior's Terror roll. If the total is greater than the Monsters' Terror Value, that Warrior is not afraid of them during this combat and may fight them as normal.</p>
<p>If the total is less than or equal to the Monsters' Terror Value, that Warrior is terrified of them during this combat, and fights them at -2 on his to hit rolls. If a Wizard fails his Terror roll any spells he attempts to cast against that Monster have their Casting Numbers increased by +2.</p>
<p>Each time the Warriors meet a particular type of Monster that causes Terror they must make a Terror roll, as the effect of the roll, whether good or bad, applies only to that type of Monster during this one combat.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-throw" name="THROW item (STR n)"><p>Some Monsters are armed with weapons that they can Throw, such a spears.</p>
<p>As soon as such Monsters are placed on the board, before the Warriors can do anything, they throw these weapons in a special, single attack. You need to roll against the Monster's Ballistic Skill to see if they hit, just as with any other missile weapon. The thrown weapon has Strength n, where n is the value in the brackets after the Throw entry. The weapon therefore causes (the Monster's damage dice)+n Wounds, modified for the target's Toughness and armour, according to the normal rules for missile weapons. A Beastman Lord with a Strength 10 spear, for instance, causes 3D6+10 Wounds, modified for Toughness and armour.</p>
<p>After throwing their special weapons these Monsters attack in hand-to-hand combat in the Monsters' Phase as normal.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-tomb-rot" name="TOMB ROT (1Dn)"><p>Some Monsters cause Tomb Rot, their mere presence rotting nearby creature's flesh. Any Warrior who ends the turn adjacent to such a Monster takes an extra 1Dn Wounds (where n is the number in brackets after the Tomb Rot entry), with no modifiers for Toughness or armour. Tomb Rot is Fatal Damage.</p>
<p>A Warrior standing next to two Mummies, for instance, takes 2D3 Wounds at the very end of each turn.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-vomit" name="VOMIT"><p>Some Monsters (namely Trolls) have a special Vomit attack, regurgitating the highly corrosive contents of its stomach all over the Warrior it is attacking.</p>
<p>In addition to making such a Monster's normal attacks, roll 1D6. If the score is a 5 or 6, the Monster has vomited on its foe. If the victim has any armour (including shields or a helmet) he loses one piece of it as the acid eats it away. The player concerned may choose which item his Warrior loses. If he hasn't got any armour, the target loses 1D6+2 Wounds, with no deductions for Toughness.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-web" name="WEB (1Dn)"><p>Certain Monsters (mainly Spiders) attempt to ensnare their prey in a Web, so that they can finish it off at their leisure. Each turn a Monster may attempt to web a Warrior as many times as it has Attacks.</p>
<p>If the Monster hits your Warrior he has been caught in its web - place a Webbed counter next to the Warrior. While webbed a Warrior may not do anything.</p>
<p>While webbed, a Warrior may be bitten automatically with the rest of the Monster's Attacks (no to hit roll is needed) for 1Dn Wounds per bite (where n is the value after the Web entry), with no modifiers for Toughness or armour. A Monster may not use its bite Attack(s) if its opponent has not been webbed. Monsters without the ability to use webs that may also be involved in the combat get +2 to their to hit rolls against a webbed Warrior.</p>
<p>At the start of each Warriors' Phase, roll 1D6 for each Warrior that has been webbed and add his Strength. If the total is 7 or more, he pulls himself free from the sticky strands and may act normally this turn.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-weeping-blade" name="WEEPING BLADE"><p>Weeping Blades are poisonous weapons.</p>
<p>If a Warrior is reduced to 0 Wounds by a Poison attack his Strength is permanently reduced by -1 when he is healed to 1 or more Wounds. If a Warrior is reduced to 0 Strength he is killed and removed from play.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-hellblade" name="HELLBLADE"><p>A Hellblade causes an extra 1D3 Wounds on the target, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-axe-of-khorne" name="AXE OF KHORNE"><p>Causes +2 Wounds. In addition, if the to hit roll of a blow made with an Axe of Khorne is a natural 6 the blow causes double damage.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-daemon-whip" name="DAEMON WHIP"><p>At the start of each turn draw a Warrior counter to determine who the Bloodthirster ensnares with the Daemon Whip. That model is immediately moved to a square adjacent to the Bloodthirster, moving other models out of the way as necessary.</p>
<p>If the Bloodthirster manages to kill a Warrior and still has some Attacks left he may switch to another target to use them.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-drain-power" name="DRAIN POWER"><p>As a powerful servant of Khorne, a Bloodthirster detests magic and has the ability to drain it from nearby spellcasters. At the start of each Monsters' Phase roll 3D6. The Wizard immediately loses that many points of Power. Each point over the amount required to drain all the Wizard's Power inflicts 1 Wound, with no modifiers for Toughness and armour. The Wizard may give up any or all of his Power Tokens to fulfil the deficit if he wishes.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-aura-of-slaanesh" name="AURA OF SNLAANESH"><p>A Fiend of Slaanesh has an Aura of Slaanesh that it can use to beguile and hypnotise its foes, holding them immobile while it attacks them. Once in combat with a Fiend of Slaanesh a Warrior cannot try to escape from pinning (and that includes the Elf!) and is at -1 to all his to hit rolls.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-slime-trail" name="SLIME TRAIL"><p>Beasts of Nurgle secrete a Slime Trail around them as they move. Any Warrior who finishes his turn in a square adjacent to a Beast of Nurgle suffers 1 Wound, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour, as the poisonous gunk attacks his flesh.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-stream-of-corruption" name="STREAM OF CORRUPTION"><p>Great Unclean Ones have a special type of attack where they vomit a foul smelling mass of pus over their foes. This is called a Stream of Corruption. A Great Unclean One may use this attack once per turn, at the start of the Monsters' Phase.</p>
<p>Any Warrior on the same board section as the Great Unclean One may be attacked with the Stream of Corruption. Draw a Warrior counter to determine which Warrior is targeted.</p>
<p>Draw a line from the centre of the Great Unclean One's Square to the target square: every square that this line passes through is affected by the Stream of Corruption (see the diagram). Roll 2D6 for each Warrior standing in a targeted square. If the score is equal to or less than his Initiative he manages to dodge the Stream and suffers no ill effects. If the score is greater than the Warrior's Initiative he suffers 3D6 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour. If a Warrior is reduced to 0 Wounds by the Stream of Corruption his Toughness is permanently reduced by -1. If a Warrior is reduced to 0 Toughness he is killed and is removed from play.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-flamer-of-tzeentch-attack" name="FLAMER OF TZEENTCH ATTACK"><p>Flamers never make a normal hand-to-hand attack. Instead, they set light to any board section that the Warriors are standing on, immolating the area with the pink fire of Tzeentch. Roll 1D6 per Flamer for each model on that board section to determine how many Wounds it suffers (normal modifiers for Toughness and armour apply). If there are 5 Flamers attacking, for instance, roll 5D6 for each model on that board section.</p>
<p>Each Flamer can make this attack once per turn (unless of course it Ambushes successfully) and they themselves are immune to the fire's effects.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-die-blue-horrors" name="DIE -> BLUE HORRORS"><p>Every time a Pink Horror is killed, two Blue Horrors spring up in its place. The Blue Horrors are placed next to the Warrior that killed the Pink Horror that spawned them. If this is not possible they can be placed in the nearest empty squares. As soon as each pair of Blue Horrors appear, make a Fear roll for each Warrior to see if he is afraid of them.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-power-of-tzeentch" name="POWER OF TZEENTCH"><p>A Lord of Change has the ability to Dispel Magic in the surrounding area, just like some other Monsters, but to a much greater degree. This ability works exactly like the normal Magic Dispel in that the Lord of Change can actively interfere with and nullify any spell cast on the board, not just those cast directly against it.</p>
<p>When dispelling magic cast against the Lord of Change's minions the spell is dispelled on a 1D6 roll of 4 or 5, and deflected back against the caster on a roll of 6. Furthermore, when dispelling beneficial magic cast by the Warriors against themselves the spell is dispelled on a 1D6 roll of 4 or 5, and affects the Lord of Change on a roll of 6.</p>
<p>A Lord of Change also has Magic Resistance just like some other Monsters, but to a much greater degree.</p>
<p>The Lord of Change has a Magic Resistance Rating of 4+. In addition, if the Resistance roll scores a 5 or 6 the spell is deflected rather than simply resisted and affects the Warrior who cast it instead. Note that Magic Resistance only protects of the Lord of Change from spells, not from blows by magical weapons and the like.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-magic-source" name="MAGIC SOURCE"><p>A Lord of Change is an extremely powerful Sorcerer and unconsciously acts as a source of power for other spellcasters. While there is a Lord of Change on the board, the Wizard doubles the result of his Power roll each turn on anything other than a roll of 1. If he rolls a l, the Wizard gets 1 point of Power, as normal.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-beast-handler" name="BEAST HANDLER"><p>Dark Elf Beastmasters control a pack of beasts in combat, directing them towards the Warriors using whips. Roll 1D6 to determine the composition of each Beastmaster's pack. On a score of 1-3 he has 1D6 Chaos Hounds. On a score of 4-6 he has 1D6 Warhounds. When placing the Beastmaster on the table, his beasts are always placed first.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-giant-attacks" name="GIANT ATTACKS"><p>Giants are huge and unpredictable creatures and it is by no means certain what form of attack they will make. At the start of each Monsters' Phase roll 1D6 on the following table for each Giant on the board to determine what it does this turn.</p>
<table>
<tr><td>1</td><td><b>Thump With Club.</b> Because of his reach the Giant can hit any Warrior up to two squares away. Take a Warrior counter to determine which Warrior is attacked. The Giant makes 1D6 attacks against the target, rolling to hit as normal. Calculate damage as normal but ignore any modifier for the target's armour.</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td><b>Swing with Club.</b> Because of his reach the Giant hits all of the Warriors up to two squares away. Roll 3D6 for each eligible target. Each dice that scores a 4, 5 or 6 causes that many Wounds, with no modifier for armour. Any dice that scores 1, 2 or 3 misses as the Warrior manages to avoid the mighty weapon.</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td><b>Kick Down Corridor.</b> <p>The Giant raises a huge booted foot and drop-kicks an adjacent Warrior into the darkness. If there is more than one eligible target draw a Warrior counter to determine who is hit. The Warrior is kicked up to 7 squares in a straight line directly away from the Giant. If he hits a wall before reaching this distance he suffers 1D6 Wounds, with no modifier for armour, for each square short of 7 he flew, plus the Giant's Strength of 7.</p>
<p>If the booted Warrior flies 2 squares then hits a wall, for instance, he suffers (7-2)=5D6 Wounds, plus 7 for the Giant's Strength, with no modifier for armour (total roll therefore equals 5D6+7).</p></td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td><b>Pick Up.</b> Because of his reach the Giant can pick up a Warrior up to two squares away. Take a Warrior counter to see who is picked up. Place that model on the Giant's base and roll 1D6 on the following sub-table:
<table>
<tr><td>1</td><td><b>Squeeze.</b> The Giant squeezes the Warrior with his mighty fist. The Warrior takes 7D6 Wounds. Roll again on this sub-table.</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td><b>Hurl at Warriors.</b> The Giant picks up the Warrior and hurls him at his companions Take a Warrior counter to see which Warrior is targeted. Roll 7D6 and separate those that have an even score from those that have an odd score. The Warrior being thrown suffers a number of Wounds equal to the sum of the even dice, while the targeted Warrior suffers a number of Wounds equal to the sum of the odd dice. Neither Warrior gets any modifiers on the damage roll for Toughness or armour. The thrown Warrior is placed prone in the square originally occupied by the target Warrior. The target Warrior is pushed into an adjacent square, shuffling other models around as necessary.</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td><b>Smash Against the Roof.</b> The Giant grabs the Warrior by the feet to get a good swing and begins to smash him repeatedly against the roof of the cave in a cheerfully enthusiastic fashion. This does the Warrior no good at all. The Giant smashes the Warrior against the roof 1D6 times, inflicting 7 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour, each time. Then roll on this sub-table again</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td><p><b>Chew.</b> The Giant begins to chew on the Warrior with teeth the size and shape of old tombstones. The Warrior suffers 1D6 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour. If the score on the dice is a 2, 3 4, 5 or 6 the Giant continues to chew the Warrior next turn, even if he is at 0 Wounds or less. Roll another 1D6 for Wounds. This process continues until the roll for Wounds is a 1 at which point the Giant finds a gristly bit, loses interest and drops the Warrior in the square he got him from. Place the Warrior prone.</p>
<p>If the Warrior is reduced to -50 Wounds the Giant swallows him whole, effectively taking him out the game.</p></td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td><p><b>Stuff into Bag.</b> The Giant picks up the Warrior and pops him into his bag, saving him for later. The inside of the bag is smelly and dark, full of all sorts of horrible things. In one corner Is a wizened old Dwarf Prospector, who wearily gives the Warrior a key and says, "This is the key to the portcullis..." in a tired and cracked voice.</p>
<p>The Warrior suffers no ill effects as long as the Giant has other foes to fight. If the Giant kills all of the other Warriors he is carried off and eaten at the Giant’s leisure. He may escape from the bag once the Giant is killed: place him in any empty square on the same board section. Once free he remains out of action for 1 turn due to shock.</p></td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td><b>Snatch and Grab.</b> The Giant pops the Warrior into his bag, as above. As it’s a long time since he had the prospect of such a juicy succulent feast the Giant reaches down for another Warrior immediately. Make another 1D6 roll on this sub-table.</td></tr>
</table>
<tr><td>5</td><td><p><b>Jump Up and Down.</b> Striking sparks off the stone floor with his hobnailed feet, the Giant jumps up and down on any single Warrior in an adjacent square. If there is more than one eligible target draw a Warrior counter to determine which Warrior is attacked. The chosen Warrior suffers 1D6 hits, taking damage for each hit as normal.</p>
<p>If the target is reduced to 0 Wounds the Giant will make another 1D6 jump attacks on the next nearest adjacent Warrior. This process continues until the Giant fails to kill a Warrior within the number of attacks he has rolled or he has reduced all adjacent Warriors to 0 Wounds.</p></td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td><p><b>Yell and Bawl.</b> Feeling a good shout coming on, the Giant bends over until his head is at the same level as the Warriors and proceeds to yell and bellow at the top of his voice.</p>
<p>Roll 2D6 for each Warrior. If the total is equal to or greater than the sum of the Warrior's Toughness and Strength he is knocked prone by the blast. He takes no Wounds from the attack.</p></td></tr>
</td></tr>
</table>
</rule>
  <rule id="rpb-wild-squig-attack" name="WILD SQUIG ATTACK"><p>At the start of the phase during which they appear, and each Monsters' Phase thereafter, roll 1D6 for each wild Squig. On a score of 1 the Squig falls asleep and does nothing this turn. On a score of 2, 3 or 4 it immediately attacks one of the Warriors. Draw a Warrior counter to see which Warrior is attacked. On a score of 5 or 6 the Squig bounds off and immediately attacks the nearest Monster. If there is more than one potential target use a dice to determine which Monster is attacked.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-dragon-breath" name="DRAGON BREATH"><p>There are many different types of dragon in the dark caverns and tunnels beneath the mountains of the Warhammer World, each with a different breath weapon (not all dragons possess the archetypal fiery breath).</p>
<p>To determine which sort of dragon the Warriors have encountered, and therefore what type of breath weapon it has, roll 1D6 on the following table:</p>
<table>
<tr><td>1-2</td><td><p><b>Fire Dragon</b> - Breathes Fire. At the start of each turn roll 1D6. The number rolled indicates how many of the Warriors are engulfed in flame and fire. If the score is higher than the number of Warriors present all of them have been hit. If not all of the Warriors are hit use the Warrior counters to determine who escapes.</p>
<p>Each Warrior hit by the fire suffers 3D6 Wounds, with no modifier for armour.</p></td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td><p><b>Black Dragon</b> - Breathes Smoke. At the start of each turn roll 1D6. The number rolled indicates how many of the Warriors are engulfed in by the oily fumes. If the score is higher than the number of Warriors present all of them have been hit. If not all of the Warriors are hit use the Warrior counters to determine who escapes.</p>
<p>Roll 1D6 for each Warrior hit by the smoke, subtract his Toughness from the score and multiply the result by 2. The total shows how many D6 Wounds the Warrior suffers, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour.</p>
<p>For example, a 6 is rolled for a Warrior of Toughness 4. He suffers ((6-4)x2)D6 = 4D6 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour.</p></td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td><b>Green Dragon</b> - Breathes Corrosive Fumes. Roll 1D6 for each Warrior and add his Toughness. If the score is 7 or more that Warrior is unaffected. If the score is 6 or less that Warrior suffers 3D6 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour.</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td><p><b>Blue Dragon</b> - Spits Electricity. Blue Dragons actually generate electricity that arcs from their mouths in the form of lightning, rather than breathe a noxious substance. Take one Warrior counter to determine who is hit. That Warrior suffers 2D6 Wounds, with no modifier for armour.</p>
<p>After resolving that attack, roll another 1D6. On a score of 3, 4, 5 or 6 the lightning bolt arcs across to another Warrior. Take another Warrior counter to determine who. He also takes 2D6 Wounds, with no modifier for armour. This process continues until the lightning bolt fails to are across to another Warrior.</p></td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td><p><b>White Dragon</b> - Breathes Chilling Mist. At the start of each turn roll 1D6. The number rolled indicates how many of the Warriors are engulfed by the mist. If the score is higher than the number of Warriors present all of them have been hit. If not all of the Warriors are hit use the Warrior counters to determine who escapes.</p>
<p>Each Warrior suffers 1D6 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour. In addition, while he thaws out, for 1 turn he has a Movement of 1, he may be hit automatically, and any dice rolls made for his actions only succeed on a natural 6. Actions that do not require you to roll a dice may be carried out as normal.</p></td></tr>
</table>
<p>A dragon's breath weapon is used in addition to its normal hand-to-hand attacks.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-treasure-hoard" name="TREASURE HOARD +n"><p>Dragons have their own treasure hoards above and beyond the treasure that is otherwise found.</p>
<p>When a dragon is killed roll 1D6+n, where n is the number after the Treasure Hoard entry, on the following table to determine what it contains:</p>
<table>
<tr><td>1</td><td>Gold. Each player may roll as many D6 as he likes, adding up the score and multiplying it by 10 to determine how much gold his Warrior finds. However, if any of the dice score a 1 his Warrior finds nothing.</td></tr>
<tr><td>2-3</td><td>Dungeon Room Treasure. Make one roll on the Dungeon Room Treasure Table for each Warrior to determine what he finds.</td></tr>
<tr><td>4-5</td><td><p>Dungeon Room Treasure and Gold. Make one roll on the Dungeon Room Treasure Table for each Warrior to determine what he finds.</p>
<p>In addition, each player may roll as many D6 as he likes, adding up the score and multiplying it by 10 to determine how much extra gold his Warrior finds. However, if any of the dice score a 1 his Warrior finds no extra gold.</p></td></tr>
<tr><td>6+</td><td>Objective Room Treasure. Make one roll on the Objective Room Treasure Table for each Warrior to determine what he finds.</td></tr>
</table>
</rule>
  <rule id="rpb-deathleap" name="DEATHLEAP"><p>Giant Rats make a special attack, called a Deathleap. Roll the Rat's attack as normal, but roll 2D6+2 for damage.</p>
<p>Once a Giant Rat has attacked your Warrior, roll 1D6. On a result of 3, 4, 5 or 6 the Giant Rat's suicidal, frenzied attack has opened it up to your Warrior's attack and he automatically kills it - place it on his Adventure Record sheet.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-sorcerous-exhalation" name="SORCEROUS EXHALATION"><p>A Lammasu breathes out whirling tendrils of magic that provide protection against magical attacks. All attacks made with a magical weapon against a Lammasu have a -2 modifier on the to hit roll.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-manticore-sting" name="MANTICORE STING"><p>During the Monsters' Phase, in addition to making its normal attacks and after it has moved, a Manticore may make a special poisonous Sting attack. Each Warrior adjacent to the Manticore is automatically hit and suffers 3D6 Wounds, modified for armour and Toughness. As this attack is poisonous. all the rules for the Poison Special Ability also apply.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-drag-and-rend" name="DRAG AND REND"><p>At the start of each turn draw a Warrior counter to determine which Warrior the Wyvern attacks. The Wyvern stretches out its long neck and attempts to ensnare and drag him nearer.</p>
<p>The Wyvern makes a normal to hit roll. If it succeeds it doesn't cause any damage, but instead has clutched the Warrior and dragged him. That model is immediately moved to the nearest square adjacent to the Wyvern, moving other models out of the way as necessary. All of the Wyvern's normal attacks are then carried out against the captured Warrior as normal. If 2 or more of these remaining attacks hit home, the Warrior has been stung.</p>
<p>Note that the targeted Warrior may only attempt to dodge the initial grab and not any subsequent attacks.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-net" name="NET"><p>Roll to hit as normal. Any Warrior hit by a net quickly becomes enmeshed. Once a Warrior has been netted by a successful to hit roll, roll 1D6 for each additional net-armed Monster attacking him who has not yet attacked him this turn but was about to do so. On a score of 1, 2 or 3 the Warrior automatically becomes ensnared by that Monster's net as well. On a score of 4, 5 or 6 the Monster instead attacks the Warrior with a club at +2 to hit, inflicting (1D6 + Strength) Wounds if he succeeds. While netted, a Warrior may not attack in any way, including magic.</p>
<p>At the start of each turn, roll 1D6 for each netted Warrior. add his Strength to the score and subtract the number of nets ensnaring him. If the score is 7 or more, he breaks free from all of the nets and may fight as normal.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-ball-and-chain" name="BALL AND CHAIN"><p>This weapon is swung around the Goblin's head and is a danger to all Warriors standing nearby and, unfortunately, to the Goblin himself. A Goblin Fanatic always attempts to get adjacent to as many Warriors as possible. At the end of each Monsters' Phase, all Warriors adjacent to a Goblin Fanatic automatically takes 1D6+3 Wounds, with no modifier for armour. However, if the damage roll is a natural 1 the Fanatic has also managed to strangle itself with its own Ball and Chain and is killed.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-herd-squigs" name="HERD SQUIGS"><p>Being rather vicious creatures, each Squig requires two Goblin Squig Hunters to control it, moving it forward with a long. pointed stick called a 'prodder'.</p>
<p>When placing Goblin Hunters and Squigs on the board, place one Squig on the board first, then the two Squig Hunters that mind it, then a second Squig and its two minders, and so on.</p>
<p>Each Squig Hunter in the team is a normal Goblin, but they must move as a pair and remain in adjacent squares. To keep control of their Squig both members of the team must be present on the same board section as the Squig.</p>
<p>As long as there are two Squig Hunters for every Squig on the board section, the Squigs never fall asleep and only attack another Squig on a natural roll of a 6 (see the Squig entry in the Monsters section of the Bestiary). If there are not enough Squig Hunters to control a Squig it becomes wild.</p>
<p>If both Squig Hunters are present in a team and they attack a Warrior with their prodder they inflict an extra 1D6 Wounds on top of their normal damage roll.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-skaven-firethrower" name="SKAVEN FIRETHROWER"><p>Skaven Warpfire Thrower teams are placed as if they were armed with missile weapons. The warpfire throwers that they carry consist of a tank of superheated warpstone connected to a gun mechanism that can spray the tainted flame across a wide area. Each warpfire thrower requires a team of two Skaven to use it. If one of the Skaven is killed the other cannot continue to use the weapon and may only make a normal hand-to-hand attack from then on.</p>
<p>At the start of the Monsters' Phase draw a Warrior counter to determine which Warrior is targeted by the team. If there is more than one team in combat, distribute their hits according to the normal One-on-one rule.</p>
<p>Each time a warpfire thrower is fired, the flames form a 1-square wide corridor that travels across the room in a straight line toward the target, hitting everything in its path.</p>
<p>If a model is hit by a warpfire thrower, it suffers 3D6 Wounds. If the dice come up with 2 or 3 natural 1's the warpfire thrower has misfired and you should roll on the following table:</p>
<table>
<tr><td>1-4</td><td>Kaboom! The warpfire thrower explodes, causing 4D6 Wounds on every model in the room. Roll 1D6 for each additional warpfire thrower in the room. On a score of 1, 2 or 3 it too blows up, causing the same damage and requiring you to make another 1D6 roll for each intact warpfire thrower, and so on.</td></tr>
<tr><td>5-6</td><td>Click-whoosh! The warpfire thrower backfires, causing 3D6 Wounds against its crew.</td></tr>
</table>
<p>In addition, roll 1D6 for each item of magical treasure the victim is carrying. On a roll of 1 the item is rendered useless for the rest of the dungeon. At the start of the next dungeon the item may be used normally again.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-skaven-jezzail" name="SKAVEN JEZZAIL"><p>Skaven jezzails are missile weapons and Skaven that carry them are placed as such. The jezzail is a Strength 5 weapon that ignores up to 3 points of the victim's armour when determining damage.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-doom-glaive" name="DOOM GLAIVE"><p>Any Warrior hit by a Doom Glaive suffers an extra 2 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-skitterleap" name="SKITTERLEAP"><p>This ability allows the Vermin Lord to disappear, move through the warp and then reappear next to its chosen victim. By moving in this way the Vermin Lord is not subject to pinning and may move through any obstacles as though they were not there.</p>
<p>If the Vermin Lord manages to kill a Warrior and still has some Attacks left he may switch to another target to use them.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-skaven-plague-censer" name="SKAVEN PLAGUE CENSER"><p>A Skaven plague censer is a heavy spiked ball on a length of chain. Make a normal hand-to-hand to hit roil against the target to determine if he is struck. If the target is hit, the censer causes iD6fStrength damage, as usual, plus the victim must make a Toughness check. Roll 1D6 and add the victim's Toughness. If the score is 7 or more he is unaffected by the fumes that surround the censer. If the score is equal to or less than 7 he takes an additional 1D3 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-death-fog" name="DEATH FOG"><p>Any Warrior adjacent to a Skaven Plague Lord is overcome by the choking, noxious vapours that surround him. At the end of every turn all adjacent Warriors take Z Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour. If a Warrior is taken to 0 Wounds by a Death Fog and is then healed his Starting Wounds score is reduced by -1D3 permanently.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-skaven-poison-globes" name="SKAVEN POISON GLOBES"><p>Skaven Poison Globadiers are missile troops and are treated just as if they were using normal missile weapons, applying all the normal missile weapon rules that implies.</p>
<p>Work out which Warriors have been hit. The poison globe attack affects those Warriors and all Warriors adjacent to them. Each affected Warrior rolls 1D6 and adds their Toughness to their score. If the total is 6 or less, the Warrior suffers 1D3 Wounds, with no modifiers for Toughness or armour.</p>
<p>However, as the globes they carry are poisoned, in addition to suffering normal damage the victim of a globe attack suffers all the effects of the Poison Special Ability. To summarise: if a Warrior is reduced to 0 Wounds by a Poison Globe his Strength is permanently reduced by -1. If a Warrior is reduced to 0 Strength he is killed and is removed from play.</p></rule>
  <rule id="rpb-vampire" name="VAMPIRE ABILITIES"><p>In addition to their hand-to-hand attacks, Vampires may make a single special attack each turn. At the start of the Monsters' Phase roll 1D6 on the following table to determine what the Vampire does this turn.</p>
<table>
<tr><td>1</td><td>Transfix. The Vampire transfixes one of the Warriors with his steely glare. Draw a Warrior counter to determine who is affected. Roll 1D6 and add that Warrior's Initiative. If the score is 11 or less he is transfixed for 1 turn. While transfixed the Warrior may do absolutely nothing and any Monster in combat with him automatically hits.</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>Regenerate. The Vampire regains 3D6 Wounds at the end of this turn, even if this takes him above his Starting Wounds score. The Vampire cannot regenerate if it is killed.</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>Bite. The Vampire bites all adjacent Warriors. Each suffers (the Dungeon level) Wounds, with no deductions for Toughness or armour. The Vampire then gains the total number of Wounds caused, adding them to his own Wounds, even if this takes him above his Starting Wounds score.</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>Ethereal. The Vampire become Ethereal 2 until the start of the next Monsters' Phase. For the duration of this state he has a Chill 3 attack rather than his normal hand-to-hand attacks.</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td>Cloak of Darkness. The Vampire gathers a mantle of blackness around him. Until the start of the next Monsters' Phase all attacks against him are made at -1 to hit. In addition, all Warriors on the same board section as the Vampire lose 1 Attack in the next Warriors' Phase.</td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td>Turns to Smoke. At the end of the Monsters' Phase, after making any hand-to-hand attack, the Vampire vanishes in a pall of smoke. Remove the model from the board. At the start of the next Monsters' Phase take a Warrior counter and place the Vampire back on the board next to that Warrior. In addition, if the Vampire left the board on less than full Wounds he returns fully healed and back up to his Starting Wounds score.</td></tr>
</table>
</rule>
</rules>